<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godlie sermon, preached on Newe yeeres day last before Sir William Fitzwilliam knight, late lord deputie of Irelande, Sir Iames Harrington knight, their ladyes and children, vvith many others, at Burghley in Rutlande. By the minister of God Anthony Anderson. Hereto is added a very profitable forme of prayer, good for all such as passe the seas: by the same author framed, and vsed in his aduentured iourney.</title>
            <author>Anderson, Anthony, d. 1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108500</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844158</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844158</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 165:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godlie sermon, preached on Newe yeeres day last before Sir William Fitzwilliam knight, late lord deputie of Irelande, Sir Iames Harrington knight, their ladyes and children, vvith many others, at Burghley in Rutlande. By the minister of God Anthony Anderson. Hereto is added a very profitable forme of prayer, good for all such as passe the seas: by the same author framed, and vsed in his aduentured iourney.</title>
                  <author>Anderson, Anthony, d. 1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Purfoote for Lucas Harison, dwelling in Paules Church yarde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1576.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes, with caption title: A forme of prayer for sea men and passengers to vse, in the sayling of shippe.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:1"/>
            <p>¶ A GODLIE Sermon, <hi>Preached on Newe yeeres</hi> day laſt, before <hi>Sir William Fitzwilliam Knight,</hi> late Lord deputie of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, <hi>Sir Iames Harrington Knight,</hi> their Ladyes and Children, vvith many others, at Burghley in Rutlande. By the miniſter of God Anthony Anderſon. <hi>Hereto is added a very profitable forme of prayer, good for all ſuch as paſſe the ſeas: by the ſame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor framed, and vſed in his aduentured iourney.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 37.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <hi>Marke the vpright man, and behold the iuſt, for the ende of that man is peace.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by</hi> Thomas Purfoote for <hi>Lucas Hariſon, dwelling in Paules Church yarde.</hi> Anno Dom. 1576.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> worſhipfull Sir William <hi>Fitzwilliam Knight, late Lorde</hi> deputie of Ireland, Sir Iames Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington Knight Maſter Ihon Harrington his ſonne and godly heire, their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Ladies, Wiues and faithfull children: <hi>Anthony Anderſon</hi> Preacher of Chriſts Gospell, wiſheth all health in Chriſt our Lorde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I vſe not (more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> briefe notes) to write my ſermons (yet right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) for that of ſome of your godly religious chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, I was more then earneſtly entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſet downe this Sermon, my ſimple newyeares gift (beſtowed in comon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you) I after lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ſute then there was great cauſe, graunted, and haue pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned downe the ſame, ſo neare as I can
<pb facs="tcp:8947:3"/> call to my memory the manner of my ſpeche. The order and diſpoſition I haue exactly obſerued, and not omitted any note or authoritie of ſcripture by me then alledged. And as it is vnpoſſible for him that penneth not his Sermons, to ſet them downe, euen ſo, and with the ſelfe ſame words in all places as he ſpake them: So to all my poſſibilitie haue I performed as neare as may be my order and ſpeech. And ſome thing haue I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſome place, which want of tyme trained me from at that preſent. And if any leſſe ye nowe lyke then when you herde the ſame, conſider then the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt reading &amp; preaching the ſelfe ſame truth, and matter. Gods grace did the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſiſt the preachers ſpirit, voice, geſture and diſpoſition, &amp; likewiſe your hartes by his ſpirite were made to hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger this holy bread. And now you haue the liuing wordes, (but ſeuered from the lyuely voyce) which neuer can bring like profit to the godly hartes, vnles greate thirſte of the matter, cauſe the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaunce of the maner howe, to ſtande as freshe before your eyes. The Lord grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it to profit as much as my good will is, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:8947:3"/> then shall my ſmall labour be fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed. I haue ioyned here to the forme of prayer which I gaue to your worship (good Sir William) at Holme Patricke in Irelande, very good for all ſuch as paſſe the ſeas, as our ſelues haue taſted by good proofe, the comforts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in our late ariual the lord be prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed therefore. Take the ſmall gyft with the geuer, all yours (as he may) in the Lorde: to whome (vvith dayly thanks for your great curteſie to me in Irelande), I in my prayers commende you &amp; the reſt vnfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>Ian. 3. 1575.</date>
               <signed>Your worships in the Lord <hi>Anthony Anderſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>The Lord is my ſheperd therfore shall I want nothing.</p>
                  <p>He maketh me to reſt in greene pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull and dearely beloued brethren, it hath from auncient dayes bene receaued, that in the firſt of the newe yeare, eache friende doth ſalute his other with ſome token of friendſhip, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wiſheth to ſuch his friende all helth &amp; good proſperitie in God. Which cyuill cuſtome in <hi>Newyeares gyfts,</hi> I do allowe in ciuill ſort, and hauing ſo many freinds here aſſembled, haue purpoſed, to benefite you all at once, and with ſuche a ſpeciall gift as of euery of you (the ſame being worthely receaued) I ſhall be deemed to haue ſatiſfied my office belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging my bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den amitie to you all. The gift I exhibit is a portion of Gods heauenly <hi>treaſure,</hi> fully ſufficient from this firſt day of the yeare to enriche you aboue meaſure in Chriſt, ſo that you vſe the ſame wyth the ſpirituall inſtrument of faithfull and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient practiſe, continually in your hartes. And this <hi>treaſure</hi> forth of the <hi>Pſalmiſts
<pb facs="tcp:8947:4"/> treaſury</hi> I haue receaued, and by the ſame ſpirit deliuer it to you in the Lord, whoſe grace the Lorde vouchſafe to be oures in this holy actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his Chriſtes ſake. The <hi>treaſure</hi> it ſelfe is the <hi>.23. <hi>Pſalme</hi>
               </hi> of the Prophet Dauid, the which Pſalme was made by that holy king, after the receipt of his kingdome and Crowne, wherto he confeſſeth God to be his onely helpe, and promiſeth to him ſelfe by the former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued benefites, an abſolute warrant of Gods heauenly prouidence in his ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Regiment. The words are thus.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord is my ſheperd, therfore ſhall I want nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He maketh me to reſt in greene paſture, and leadeth me by the ſtill waters.</hi> And ſo forth to the ende of the Pſalme.</p>
            </q>
            <p>I purpoſe (hauing thus by prayer cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god) to giue you the Pſal. by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and of euery of them ſuch comfortable leſſons, as the Lorde in mercy ſhall gyue me to vtter vnto your Chriſtian hartes, and with as much breuitie as may be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the extreme cold, that ſo we may more ſpeedely approche the Lordes holy Table to receiue his heauenly myſteries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord is my ſheperd. &amp;c.</hi> The prophet
<pb facs="tcp:8947:5"/> calleth his God a <hi>ſhepherd,</hi> becauſe of his prouident care ouer him one of his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen lambes, which word <hi>(ſheperd)</hi> impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth an office of continual feeding, of day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care, of ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t loue to the flocke vnder his charge, of watching, guiding and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, to the beſt ſafety of his ſheepe. All which the noble Dauid, by the ſpirite of Gods inſtructiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knoweth to be in the Lord, his &amp; our god, &amp; therfore he giueth his maieſtie, this moſt apt tytle: <hi>The Lord is my ſheperd.</hi> Dauid the prophet vſeth the phraſe which God by his holy ſpirite gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to him &amp; his other Prophets in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Lord a ſheperd,<note place="margin">Pſa. 77.21 Pſal. 80.1.</note> as thus. <hi>Thou diddeſt lead thy people lyke ſheepe by the hand of Moſes and Aaron.</hi> Againe, <hi>O thou ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perd of Iſraell herken which leadeſt Ioſeph lyke a ſheepe.</hi> And when God will by his Prophet foretell in what ſorte he will viſite his people,<note place="margin">Eſai. 40.11</note> he promiſeth his viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Chriſt by this name, ſaying: <hi>He ſhall feede his flocke lyke a ſheperde, he ſhall gather the lambes with his arme, and cary them in his boſome, and ſhall guide them with young.</hi> Lykewiſe in the Prophet Iere. 23.4. &amp; Ezec. 34.10.12.<note place="margin">Pſa. 110.1 Ma. 23. Act. 2.34.</note> This ſheperd Chriſt is Dauids ſheperd and Lord. <hi>The Lord ſaid vnto my Lord, ſit thou on my right hand, vntil
<pb facs="tcp:8947:5"/> I make thine enemies thy footeſtole.</hi> In which place Dauid calleth Chriſt his lord, which is to hſm &amp; to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> choſen children of god the appointed ſheperd of their ſoules, as Chriſt him ſelfe doth witnes, ſaying:<note place="margin">Io. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>J am the good ſheperd,</hi> the good ſheperde giueth his lyfe for his ſheepe. And Peter in his firſt epiſtle thus:<note place="margin">1. Pe. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>Ye were as ſheepe going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray but ye are returned now vnto the ſheperd and byſhop of your ſoules.</hi> In a good ſheperd are to be required theſe things, all which are moſt aptly found in Chriſte our good ſheperde. He muſt be of ſounde ſkill, to know his ſheepe from other mens cattel, &amp; this is ſaid of Chriſt, I know my ſhepe by name, &amp; am knowne of mine. He muſt haue ſkill in paſturing his ſheepe, leaſt he bring them to rotten ſoyle, and waſting graſſe. In Chriſte is the onely paſture of mans ſoule, in whom all ſafetie of foode is, for his glorious goſpel is our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foode, his ſpirite &amp; life is our celeſtiall diet, &amp; by the mouth of our faith, this our bread of lyfe is of euery of vs that beleue, firmely eaten, and the ſame is ſo ſounde and ſweete paſture, that no rot and death can come vnto the worthy fieldes,<note place="margin">Io. 5.24.</note> or any leſſe able is yt then his
<pb facs="tcp:8947:6"/> diuine power to bring vs to life eternall. Thirdly a good ſheperde muſt haue will to feede according to his ſkill, that ſo his ſheepe may not be pyned for want of his louing paynes: So Chriſt is moſt louing of all others to feede his lambes, who hath not ſpared to lay downe his lyfe for the foode of his ſheepe. willing to feede, for he calleth all men to hym for paſture. moſt carefull of their diet,<note place="margin">Io. 10.15. Mat. 11.28</note> and therfore he hath left their <hi>Pabulum</hi> his holy worde to the ende of the world, whereby his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſheepe ſhoulde become fatte and well lyking in him, and hath to this ende com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded Peter to feede,<note place="margin">Io. 21.15.16.17.</note> &amp; alſo hath from thence tyll nowe, and will to the ende of this worlde ſelect his paſtors from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, to feede men with the breade of life, Chriſt in his word &amp; Sacraments. Further a good Sheperd taketh greate eare ouer his ſheepe, and vigilantly doth ſearch if ſo any of them ſkabbe, or be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and finding them faultie, hee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſeth him ſelfe to their amendment: ſo Chriſte our Lorde doth dearely care ouer his flocke,<note place="margin">Act. 20.28. Luke. 15.4 5.</note> they be to him as the apple of his eye for them he hath payd the price of their ſynne, and deadly diſeaſe, namely
<pb facs="tcp:8947:6"/> his owne heart blood, he ſeeketh the loſt and caryeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on his owne ſhoulders,<note place="margin">Mat. 18 12 Lu. 10.34.</note> he annoynteth their ſores with the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne ſalue of his mercy and iuſtice:<note place="margin">Eſai. 53. 1. Pe. 2.24.</note> with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one he pacifieth, and that becauſe he fully ſatiſfieth his iuſt Father: with the other he couereth our ſins &amp; healeth our infirmities. He moſt louingly loketh into our weakenes, and beareth vp our infancy, he breaketh not the bruſed rede,<note place="margin">Ma. 12.20.</note> nor quencheth the ſmoking flaxe. He ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth not our lyues to be laſciuious, but ſcourgeth and purgeth vs, that we may bring forth more frute.<note place="margin">Io. 15.2.</note> Laſtly a good ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perd hath himſelfe, his ſtaffe &amp; ſheperdes dog, to help &amp; aide his wandering flocke. Euen ſo hath Chriſte giuen him ſelfe for our defence,<note place="margin">Io. 15.2.3.</note> his preaching prophets haue of him eſpeciall charge to feede his flocke, and them protect continually:<note place="margin">Eze. 3.18. Act. 20.28.</note> and great plagues hath he appointed to ſuche ydle ſheperds as no way fede his lowly la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes: and though all men faile,<note place="margin">Zach. 11.17</note> yet Dauid byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs all be glad, for the Lorde is our ſheperd therfore ſhall we not want. And now dearely beloued, tyme and place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth to ſpeake ſomething of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſheepes propertie, which belong to that ſheperde
<pb facs="tcp:8947:7"/> Chriſte, the which thing knowne, euery man and woman with their young ones, may with examination of them ſelues, beſt ſay to God, I am thy ſhepe, for thou O Lorde art my ſheperd. For of no other is Chriſt the Sheperd, but of thoſe which know their wandring wickednes, &amp; feele their ſtaie to ſtand in him their God, and ſpedely ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues vnder his tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And to this is Dauid our guide, who notwithſtanding he was rich and a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty king, yet he freely confeſſeth his health to be in this, that he is the Lords ſheepe, &amp; hath Chriſte to his euerlaſting ſheperd. In a ſheepe are ſundry thinges agreeing, with the corruption of our nature, and therefore ſtandeth in great neede of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert ſheperde. She is fooliſhe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares of harmes, ſhe runneth into dayly daungers in her ſelfe remediles: So we by nature are vnwiſe, and blynde to all heauenly thinges.<note place="margin">Rom. 8</note> Or can the naturall man ſauor the thinges which be of God, or yet keepe hym from the wandring pathes of death.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> The wandring wayes of all the beſte may ſet downe this: to the other ſorte, for all to true, that man can not but ſinne and dayly runne from God
<pb facs="tcp:8947:7"/> the Lorde. Our Dauid he, may ſtande as able among the reſt, to this for profe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any in the fleſhe by the qualities fleſhy pleaſe God.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> A ſheepe for weakenes and want of courage is vnable to ſtande agaynſte ſo many her deuouring foes, the Foxe, the Wolfe, and the rauenous Lyon: nor is the ſtouteſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth by nature, of power to gyue checke vnto ſynne, who like a ſubtill Foxe lyeth lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and fawning for his pray of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſoule: or from the gaping gulfe, of woluiſhe chappes that hipocritically ſeeke his ſpoyle:<note place="margin">1. Pe. 5.</note> or yet from the raging Satan, who goeth roring abroade ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king euery where who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deuour. The good ſheperde Chriſte therefore is moſte requiſite, in whom againſt all theſe we may goe in and out ſafely,<note place="margin">Io. 10.</note> and finde paſture.</p>
            <p>But els the naturall ſheepe hath qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities right good, which are frequented in the children of God, they know their Paſtors whyſtle, and thereat they yelde vnto his will. So the ſheepe of Chrſte refuſing all ſtraunge voyce, they herken vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of our ſauiour Chriſt, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:8947:8"/> they take ſuch comfort as hauing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in full contentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they eſchew all others charme, be they neuer ſo ſubtill, &amp; ſly. The ſheepe is euer feding with his flece thoſe, which no way haue pleaſured him, for he hath his lyfe of his ſheperdes paſture. So the children of God, lyuing in their Chriſt, are beneficiall to all for his names ſake.<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.7.</note> The ſheepe is laid by the ſherer to the loſſe of him ſelfe, vpon the thrall, and yet he openeth not his mouth: So alſo the true chriſtian abideth for his Chriſt all ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.3 4. &amp;c.</note> &amp; reprochful death not reſiſting at al, but willingly abydeth the croſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the euent in the Lord, which is to them that ſuffer for his names ſake euer proſperous. Now my brethren of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors condition claſped in Chriſte and of the ſheepes nature fixed by his ſpirite, learne your ſelues to know to whom ye belong, and yf you feele your ſelues the <hi>Foldimates</hi> of Dauid, then may you be bold to ſay, <hi>The Lord is my ſheperd therfore can I not want.</hi> The wants whereof the prophet here ſpeaketh are of two ſortes. The one is called inſaciable luſt, the other neceſſarie nede. With the firſt as the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are not combred (for that belongeth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:8947:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> the reprobate) ſo the other in them is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer remedied by the feeding ſheperde Chriſt, firſt in ſupplying their neede with preſent neceſſaries: then in forming their harts to be content with their eſtate, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by his diuine prouidence, to his glorie and their beſte good.<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.25</note> 
               <hi>I haue bene young and now am I olde</hi> (ſayth Dauid) <hi>yet neuer ſawe I the righteous forſaken, or his ſeede begging their breade.</hi> Helias fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his vocation,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 17.4 5.6.</note> was forſaken of all men, but dayly fed of God by the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenous Crowes, &amp; the poore wydowes meale, when the riche gluttons of Iſraell were pined for want of neceſſarie foode.<note place="margin">1. Kin. 17.14.15.16. Dan. 14. ſtory of Bell.</note> Daniell ſeeking chiefly the glory of our God is caſt into the hungry Lyons den in deede, but preſerued to lyue, and to him is ſent the prophet Abacucke with his dinner many a myle by the guide of an Angell. The Iewes which folowe Chriſt into the wildernes are of him mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly fed.<note place="margin">Io. 6.11.12 13. Mat. 6.33. Pſa. 37.19</note> And to all is this promiſe gyuen. <hi>Seeke firſt the kindome of God and the righteouſnes therof, and all other thinges ſhall be myniſtred vnto you.</hi> Now as concerning that the Lord frameth his peoples harts to be contented with their eſtate. Paule
<pb facs="tcp:8947:9"/> for the body of the whole churche, ſayeth thus:<note place="margin">Phi. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>I haue learned in what ſtate ſoeuer I am therwith to be content, &amp; I can be abaſed &amp; I can abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, euery where in all things I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, both to be full &amp; to be hungry, &amp; to a bound,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 37.2.3 Pſa. 17.14</note> 
               <hi>and to haue want.</hi> The wicked many tymes do floriſhe as the greene bay tree, and haue the worlde at will, great ſtore of welth for them ſelues and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo that their ſonne ſonnes doo feede of the elder gotten bread, but withall they haue their portion in this lyfe, and after that can ſee no further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts. And though the godly contrary do feele many wants, and ſeeme in mans conceipt vtterly to decay, yet far other is their ſtate then externall ſhewe doth tell, For the Lord is their ſheperde, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſeeme to dye, they lyue: they are chaſtened, but not killed: they ſeeme in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to be ſwallowed vp, but they alway reioyce:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.8.9.10.11.16.17.18. 2. Cor. 6.9.10.</note> they ſeeme poore, but yet they make many rich: &amp; depriued ſo of worldly comforts ſeeming to haue nothing, they notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding poſſeſſe all things. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their ende is farre otherwiſe then the worldly riche. For the Lorde dealeth with them as the noble man with his fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Oxe, when he is well fedde, is by the
<pb facs="tcp:8947:9"/> ſlaughter man committed to the axe of death, his noble ſonne abydeth many ſharp yirkes and correcting blowes, and after that enioyeth his fathers poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Euen ſo the wicked in wealth are wrapped with Diues in hell, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued (though payned Lazarus) is caried by ſeruice of Angels into our heauenly Fathers kingdome,<note place="margin">Luke. 16</note> our Chriſtes inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaunce belonging to the iuſt. This is the marke that Dauid ſhooteth at when he ſayth, <hi>I ſhall not want.</hi> It followeth,</p>
            <q>He ſhall make me to rest in greene pasture,<note place="margin">verſ.2</note> he leadeth me by the ſtyll vvaters.</q>
            <p>All things neceſſarie ſhall the Lorde geue me ſayth Dauid, and that in no baſe ſort, or ſhall any trouble moleſt my feeding? for I ſhal quietly be guyded, and my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie ſhall be continuing, alwayes flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing greene, and at no tyme dry or wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, neyther ſhall his bleſſinges be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from me with the rage of wicked men: but as the ſhepe, of her ſelfe weake, needeth reſting place, and quiet riuers: ſo ſhall all thinges come to the beſt, and to my hartes deſire in him. But beloued in Chriſt, our ſhepheard is ſpiritual, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our paſture muſt be anſwerable, and
<pb facs="tcp:8947:10"/> it is ſet downe to vs by our maſter &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, thus:<note place="margin">Io. 5.24</note> 
               <hi>He that heareth my vvorde, and beleeueth on him that ſent me, hath eternall lyfe, and he ſhall not come into iudgement, but hath paſſed from death vnto lyfe.</hi> Heere is the paſture of life the goſpell of God: The reſt for mans ſoule, fayth in God through Chriſte:<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.39.</note> The ſtill waters, the holye ſpirite whiche dothe pacifie the troubled conſcience, and quietly eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth vs in Chriſte, who freeth vs from the Fathers iuſlice, the ſentence of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death, and giueth vs hys glorious Crowne, and heauenly kingdome our inheritaunce in him. Come to this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.14.</note> feede on this bread, reſt in this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, drinke of this water, So ſhall you no more thirſt after the filthy puddles of Popiſhe poyſoned Cuppes. For in your ſelues (by this ſpirite of Chriſte) ſhall abundant riuers of ſpirituall goodnes flowe out of you, that all men ſeeing your good workes,<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> may bee prouoked to prayſe the Lorde. This God graunt you for his ſonne our ſauiour Chriſt his ſake. Amen.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 3.</note>He ſhall conuert my ſoule, &amp; leade me in the pathes of righteouſnes, for his names ſake.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:10"/>
            <p>Three eſpeciall thinges in this verſe the Prophet teacheth moſte notably. Firſte, that we are by nature ſtubborne, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraunged from the nature belonging the ſheepe of God. Secondly, that after rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration by the ſpirite, there remayneth yet in vs ſuch matter of maſſy ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.18.19.20.</note> that vnable we be to walke the pathes belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the children of god, and therefore it behoueth vs to haue a leader into righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes. Thirdly, as many be the falles by ſinne which Satan and the fleſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth to vs: So ſundrie be the fruites of the godly. In whiche vertues, as in ſinne, Satan ſeeketh our ouerthrowe, if ſo he can make vs to reſte in them, as eyther ſatiſfactorie to God, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious for their valor. But the Lord by his Prophet here preacheth, that our conuerſion to god, &amp; our walking dayly in godlynes, is from &amp; by the Lorde, and that alſo not for any preuenting, forekno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne, or ſucceeding graces in vs: but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoly for hys names ſake. He ſhall conuerte my ſoule, ſayth Dauid. The roote of the Tree beeing ſounde and good, feedeth hir braunches to hir fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full life: So the ſoule of mans principall
<pb facs="tcp:8947:11"/> ſubſtaunce beeing made whole &amp; ſounde, can not but geue life to the whole body. In this braunche alſo we are to note, that vnles the inwarde man be turned vnto God, thexternall partes can be but hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall, and ſeruing time. So the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in <hi>Ioaſh</hi> Court, during the dayes of the good Byſhop <hi>Jehoiada,</hi> ſeemed moſte religious,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 24 17.18.19.20.</note> but death had no ſooner depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the godly of this Prieſtes life, then they diſwaded the Prince, &amp; to their earſt ydolatrie perſwaded they him. Many be the mouthes that nowe confeſſe them ſelues changed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Popiſh life, but God continue our noble Elizabethes raigne, and the Goſpell ſafe progreſſe, els doubt I that ſtormy dayes would ſterue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmal ſtore of liuing grace, in many Engliſhe hartes of ſundry callings. But who ſo is turned in hart and minde vnfaignedly, he ioyeth the dayes of dangerous death, and ſoroweth to ſee the worldly ſolace, the cauſe no doubt of all infinite woes.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> He hateth that he loued firſt, he lotheth at his former lyfe, he is aſhamed of ſinne, he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth off from him the works of darknes, and confeſſing Chriſte with his lippes, becauſe he beleeueth on him in harte,
<pb facs="tcp:8947:11"/> he dayly walketh in the pathes of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes after his leader Chriſt our lord. And here with me note, good Auditorie, who it is that doth conuert mans ſoule, him ſelfe, or ſome other: the Lorde our Shepheard, Dauid ſayth it is, <hi>He ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert my ſoule.</hi> In that we are conuerted, it is not our action, or in our power is it to become the ſheepe of Chriſte, but it is the worke of God in him. The order alſo in our conuerſion to the Lorde is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. The Father geueth to his Chriſte thoſe whiche ſhall be called.<note place="margin">Io. 17.2.6</note> The holy Ghoſt he giueth into their hartes, whom he hath predeſtinate to lyfe, which ſpirite graffeth them into Chriſte, who by his blood doth waſh their ſoules from ſinne, and by the ſame his ſpirite doth forme them in his fayth, whoſe Goſpell he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in their hartes, and ſheedeth his loue into their conſciences, ſo that they walke in newnes of lyfe, becauſe they are taken vp, and the olde man in them caſt downe, and as newe creatures they follow their leader Chriſte, into the ſteppes beſitting their condition. Theſe are they whiche are <hi>theodidaktoi,</hi> all taught of God. This elegant order is deſcribed at large by the
<pb facs="tcp:8947:12"/> Prophet Ezechiell, in this ſort: <hi>A newe hart vvill I geue you, and a new ſpirite vvill I put vvithin you, &amp; I vvill take away the ſtony hart out of your body, and vvill geue you an hart of fleſh, and I vvill put my ſpirite vvithin you, and cauſe you to vvalke in my ſtatutes, and you ſhall keepe my iudgements, and do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And a little after, <hi>I vvill be your God, and you ſhall be my people:</hi> And agayne thus, <hi>Then ſhall ye remember your owne vvicked vvayes, and your deedes vvhiche vvere not good, and ſhall iudge your ſelues vvorthy to haue bene deſtroyed for your iniquities and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations. Be it knowne to you that J doo not this for your ſakes,</hi> ſayth the Lord God, <hi>therefore be aſhamed and confounded for your owne vvayes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.29</note> And Paule to the Romanes hath it thus, <hi>Thoſe which he knew before, he alſo predestinate to be made like to the image of his ſonne, that he might be the firſt borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many brethren.</hi> Moreouer, <hi>Whom he predestinate, them alſo he called, and whom he called, them alſo he iustified, and vvhom he iustified, them alſo he glorified.</hi> This is the golden gifte of god, thus is oure newe creation lincked in this precious chayne.<note place="margin">Eph. 1.2.3.4.</note> The celeſtiall god hath inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beyonde tyme predeſtinate and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:8947:12"/> his people to the likeneſſe of hys ſonne, and hath by his holy ſpirite ſealed them to him ſelfe, and by thexternal Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his holy worde, through the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of preaching, in their ſeuerall times hath he called his ſheepe to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their ſhepheard Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> and ſtate in him, and by his bloody death hath iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified them before, and with his ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall power hath made them glorious with the Angels. So our conuerſion,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.</note> as it is by the Lord, ſo is it by his ſpirite and goſpell wrought in vs. Howe neceſſarie then the office of preaching is, you ſee, it is the inſtrumentall cauſe of our conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. How miſerable that place is which wanteth preaching, may you perceyue by the glory that commeth through dayly teaching Chriſt by the truth in his word. For this cauſe Chriſte ſo often,<note place="margin">Math. 3. 2. Co. 5.20</note> Iohn Baptiſt ſo diligentlye, the Prophetes ſeuerely, the Apoſtles moſte playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, the Paſtours and ſpirituall ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards in Gods Churche nowe moſte comfortablye, doe offer and exhibite vnto you the trueth of God to tourne your heartes. By the preaching of the worde, the worlde from tyme to tyme
<pb facs="tcp:8947:13"/> hath bene wonne to Chriſte the ſonne of God: and by the ſame the Gentiles are conuerted into him: hereby this nation is chaunged into truth, and Popery ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen: by this ſhall the hartes of the children he turned to the fayth of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in God,<note place="margin">Luke. 1.17</note> and the Reprobate ſhall heerewith be condemned. And this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie Dauid giueth to the worde: The Lawe of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19</note> ſayth he, conuerteth the ſoule, the teſtimonie of the Lorde is faythfull, and giueth light vnto the eyes. The neceſſitie of teaching Paul preacheth to be great:<note place="margin">1. Co. 9.16</note> woe vnto me if I preache not (ſayth he).<note place="margin">Pro. 29.18</note> where preaching fayleth, the people periſh, ſayth Salomon. Fayth commeth by hearing of the word of God, ſayth Paule to the Romaines:<note place="margin">Ro. 10.17</note> without fayth can not a man pleaſe God: by faith we ſhall be more then conquerours:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.37</note> he that beleeueth ſhall be ſaued,<note place="margin">Mark. 16 16</note> but he that beleeueth not ſhall be damned, ſayth our doctor Chriſte. Fayth is brought by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, hearing wayteth of the Preacher, the Preacher is dombe vnleſſe he be ſent: pray therefore the Lorde of truth, to ſend more ſtore of true &amp; paynfull Preachers into this Churche of Englande, and this
<pb facs="tcp:8947:13"/> ſhire, and conuert in mercy, or confound by Iuſtice,<note place="margin">Eſa. 56.10 11.12</note> theſe dombe Dogges whiche can not barke: theſe watchemen whiche can not ſee: theſe ydol ſhepheards which eyther can not, or will nor feede the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Lambes of Gods holy Church, and ſhepefold of this nation. O Lord graunt this for thy Chriſt our chiefe ſhepheards ſake. Now deare freends examine your ſelues here preſent: Is this holy chaunge wrought in you? maye I ſay vnto you with Paule, <hi>Ye were ſometime Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 1</note> 
               <hi>ye vvere dead in ſinne, ye vvere without God in this lyfe?</hi> But you hath he quickened: you hath he called: you that were no people, hath he nowe made the people of God: you are no more ſtraungers and forre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but Citizens with the Saincts, and of the houſholde of God, buylt (not vpon the Romiſhe rocke, but) vpon the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Apoſtles and Prophetes,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.19</note> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte him ſelfe beeing the head cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone: in whom (my brethren) if you be by his ſpirite grafted and buylt, you ſhall growe to an holy temple in the lord. I truſt to you I may ſay thus: Ye were Gentiles, but you are Chriſtians, of the cheefeſt I knowe it, of the reſt I haue
<pb facs="tcp:8947:14"/> great cauſe to thinke it, and therfore with great comfort in God, I proceede to the ſecond point. <hi>He leadeth vs in the pathes of righteouſnes for his names ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In God is our conuerſion, in him alſo is the continuance of our vpright wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king before him. Firſt, of vs is here to be noted a double righteouſnes, whervnto we are brought by Chriſt. The firſt is the righteouſnes of Chriſt for vs to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The ſeconde is the righteouſnes of man by Chriſte, and is the worthy wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in holines of lyfe without ceaſſing. The righteouſneſſe of Chriſt for vs,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.12.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in the perſon of him ſelfe, who for vs hath ſo anſwered the fathers full iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, in his iuſte ſacrifice, and hath ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate vs into him ſelfe, by fayth throughe his ſpirite, that the ſame his righteouſneſſe is accompted for ours, ſo that though we by nature are wicked, yet in reſpecte of his grace we are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and iuſt in the ſight of God, whoſe it is to ſaue and to condemne. Of this iuſtification or righteouſnes Paule ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thus.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>God ſending his owne ſon downe in the ſimilitude of ſinfull fleſhe, for ſinne condemned ſinne in the fleſhe that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:8947:14"/> of the lawe, might be fulfilled in vs, which walke not after the fleſhe, but after the ſpirite.</hi> The ſeconde righteouſneſſe is the dayly walking in newnes of lyfe, which is of euery man required that thus by the Lord is iuſtified. The grace of God (ſayth Paule) that bringeth ſaluation vnto all men appeared,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.11.</note> and teacheth vs that we ſhoulde deny vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlyneſſe and worldly luſtes, and that we ſhould lyue ſoberly and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and godly in this worlde, loking for the bleſſed hope and appearing of the glory of the mightie God, and of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte, who gaue him ſelfe for vs, that he might redeeme vs from all iniquitie, and purge vs to be a peculiar people vnto him ſelfe, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of good workes. Into both of theſe Chriſte leadeth vs, for of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues we are vnapt, inable and moſte vnworthy, had we power to enter into the firſte, to winne the latter. Dayly we be looking backe from the plough, where vnto we are brought by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Lu. 9.62.</note> therefore vnapte of oure ſelues to his kingdome. wee haue not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8947:15"/> much power as to think a good thought, but that ſufficiencie which ſeemeth to be in any of vs,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.5</note> the ſame is of God, who doth both beginne the worke of God,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.6</note> and performe the ſame in vs. The better lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned we be in God, the more fully we ſee our vnworthines, to be accompted mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his righteouſnes. As the Prophet Ezechiell ſayth,<note place="margin">Ezech. 35.30.31</note> I will deliuer you from all your filthines, &amp;c. Then ſhall yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your own wickednes, and your deedes that were not good, &amp; ſhall iudge your ſelues worthy to haue bene deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Zacheus was the beſt diſpoſed man in that people, and the more graces he had with the Centurion, the more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy he thought him ſelfe of Chriſtes preſence at his houſe: but beeing comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt, he tooke moſt ioy therein. Finally, let vs note the valor of this worde, <hi>He leadeth vs.</hi> That we are righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous before God, it is that Chriſte our ſhepheard leadeth vs by his ſpirite, and fayth, vnto the throne of grace, where he preſenteth vs as deare children to God his father, and teacheth vs to crye vnto him,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.18 Rom. 8.15</note> 
               <hi>Abba</hi> deare father. Into which ſtate by his ſpirite brought, we firmely ſee our
<pb facs="tcp:8947:15"/> ſaluation to reſt in him, and that we are ſealed to the Lordes ſaluation.<note place="margin">Apoc. 7. and 14 Eph. 4.30 1. Io. 5.10</note> Yea and the witnes euen Gods holy ſpirite from that Throne, is ſet ſtrongly in our harts, and within vs doth beare witnes againſt Satan, ſinne, and the worlde, that follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing our God by the fayth of Chriſt, we are become his children, ſo righteous that no man can conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vs, becauſe our god hath in his Chriſte ſet vs free.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.33 2.</note> To the ſeconde he leadeth vs in him ſelfe firſt: as Peter ſayth, <hi>Christ ſuffered for vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.21</note> 
               <hi>leauing vs an example that we ſhould followe his ſteps, vvho did no ſinne, neyther vvas there any guyle founde in his mouth, vvho vvhen he vvas reuiled, reuiled not agayne, vvhen he ſuffred, he threatned not, but committed it to him that iudgeth righteouſly.</hi> Secondly, by his holy ſpirite he conducteth vs into all goodnes.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.14</note> For eyther are we lead by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and fleſhe vnto euill, or by his ſpirite and grace into all godlynes.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.19</note> In our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues there is no power of paſſing to good, or will to ſtay from euill.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.19</note> Of whom ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a man is ouercome, his ſeruaunt he is ſayth the Apoſtle, whether of ſinne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, or of grace vnto lyfe. And thoſe which be the ſonnes of God, are lead by
<pb facs="tcp:8947:16"/> the ſpirite of God, and ſtrengthned in the inner man,<note place="margin">Eph. 3.16.</note> Chriſt dwelleth in their harts by faith, they are rooted and grounded in the loue of God, they are by Chriſt cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled one to another in him, through him they receiue the increaſe of the ſpirituall body, &amp; edify one another: and therefore they walke not as other Gentiles, or them ſelues earſt did, in the vanitie of their mynde, with darkened cogitations in blynde hipocriſie, but they caſte of the old man and paſſed conuerſation, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus renued, they put on the newe, which is created in righteouſnes &amp; true holines after the will of God.<note place="margin">Eph. 4.19 20.</note> Thus they folow by the ſpirite the commaundement of Paule in Chriſt, ſaying: <hi>Be ye followers of God as deare childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.4.</note> And him ſelf going before hath giuen vs a rule to meaſure the ſaintes imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying: <hi>Folow you me, as J folowe Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.1</note> The Lord graunt vs his grace and ſpirituall ſtrength by proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and aduerſitie, ſycknes and health, lyfe &amp; death, thus to folow our leader, and paſtor Chriſte Ieſus, in true holineſſe and righteouſnes before him all the daies of this our preſent lyfe.<note place="margin">Luk. 2.</note> I dwell in ſpeche to teach the ſheepe of God onely,
<pb facs="tcp:8947:16"/> and therefore I leaue to ſet you forth the pathes of the wicked goates, whiche knowe not God, nor can be accepted of him.<note place="margin">Sap. 5.</note> They runne through the pleaſures of this lyfe, and lyue at luſte, till death do ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon their ſoules to the tribunal throne whence they are caſte to euerlaſtinge torments and woe. But or we paſſe this verſe, we ought depely to conſider the concluſion of Dauids words which are: <hi>This hee doth for his names ſake.</hi> From the beginning the godly haue felt his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending and guiding hande, &amp; by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite they haue bene fedde and ledde the wayes to lyue in him, but neuer was there any one, or could the worthines of all, being layd vp into one lumpe, deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the leſt his benefits, or euer challenge cauſe beyonde his owne names ſake to moue his ſo greate mercy to his choſen churche and children. For his names ſake he hath conuerted and ledde vs, that is for his owne glories ſake, and not our worthyneſſe hath hee thus bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs. Then thus the Prophet ſayth: <hi>That the Lorde is our ſhepheard,</hi> that he hathe choſen vs from the wicked woorlde to be of the nomber of his
<pb facs="tcp:8947:17"/> elect children and ſheepe of his paſture, that he temporally feedeth vs: that he by his ſpirite, and the miniſterie of his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell conuerteth vs: that he maketh vs righteous before his Father in him, and leadeth vs by the hande into all godly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and chriſtian lyfe: that he conduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs into ſafetie from the furie of our crooked foes, and euery way bleſſeth vs: it is not for the excellencie of our beautie, for that is but graſſe:<note place="margin">Eſa. 40 Eſa. 30.22. Eſa. 64 verſ. 6</note> not for our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, for that is to his eyes as a filthy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous cloth. But it is for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame cauſe wherwith he hath euer bin prouoked, and that is, <hi>for his owne glories ſake.</hi> So haue the Fathers from time to time confeſſed, condemning them ſelues for ſinne, and accepting his benefites for his mercye ſake, and his holy names ſake. This is that the Prophet would haue vs to reſte in, when he ſayth, that the name of god is a ſtrong Towre of defence. For his names ſake he will leade vs, and nouriſh vs: for his great names ſake he will not forſake his people:<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.4 1. Sa. 12.22 Eſa. 48.9 Eze. 20.9</note> and for his names ſake he will farre hence remoue his anger from vs. The ſame ſhall cauſe him to preſerue his truth among the gentiles.
<pb facs="tcp:8947:17"/> And that he continueth his goſpell, our gracious Queene and this quiet gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ouer vs, it is not for our worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who be all for our dayly ſinnes moſt vnworthy of his mercyes, as the Lorde for euer ſpeaketh to all fleſhe thus:<note place="margin">Eze. 36.32.</note> 
               <hi>Be it knowne vnto you that I do not this for your ſakes:</hi> No Lorde, but for thine own names ſake, to the which, only be all glory for euer. It foloweth.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 4.</note> And though I ſhould walke through the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of the ſhadowe of death, J will feare no euill, for thou art euer with me. Thy rodde and thy ſtaffe they comfort me.</q>
            <p>The leſſons againe be three in eſpeciall whiche Dauid hath taught me in this verſe to deliuer you. The firſt is, though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the godly ſafely are ſet vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes protection, as the ſheepe vnder the moſt faithfull ſhepheard, yet are they aſſaulted with ſundry attempts,<note place="margin">Pſa. 34.19</note> and eminent daungers. <hi>Many be the troubles of the iuſt</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>but the Lorde deliuereth him quite out of all.</hi> And his mercy hath ſo determined the matter, that the godly perceauing his holy hande, might more firmely reſte in his fatherly prouidence. Secondly the godly are not freede vnder
<pb facs="tcp:8947:18"/> the ſhepheard Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all kind of feare, but are ſet amid the mightie helhounds of the earth,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.7</note> that they ſhould warely walke and ſhunne thoccaſion of daunger, but if they be ſo exalted by the Lord, to haue the croſſe, then are they freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhaking ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.13</note> &amp; deſperat feare, &amp; ſtrengthned by his ſpirit: they follow Chriſt whither ſoeuer he goeth.<note place="margin">Exo. 14.22</note> So the Iſraelites folowed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the Red ſea, ſo the children y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angel in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> burning Ouen,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.25.</note> So Thapoſtles their maſter Chriſt to death &amp; cruell torments. So Dauid without feare is redy to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his calling though he paſſe through the valley of the ſhadow of death, that is, though he enter into moſt extreme perill. The third is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boldning force which Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pteth by his ſhepherds croke, <hi>Thy rod &amp; thy ſtaffe they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort me.</hi> Two things ſayth Dauid driue al feare from me. Thy preſence, for thou art with me: &amp; thy care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful gouernment, which is always exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to my good. Note good people, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god is alwais preſent, &amp; beholdeth al our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; perceth into our thoughts: he ſawe Sara in Abimelecks cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber,<note place="margin">Gen. 20.3</note> &amp; Bethſaba in Dauids bed.<note place="margin">2. Sa. 12.1.</note> He preuented Herodes purpoſe, &amp; brought confuſion to Saules
<pb facs="tcp:8947:18"/> perſecution.<note place="margin">Pſa. 22.24</note> He beholdeth the oppreſſion of the poore afflicted, &amp; is preſent to heare their cry when they call vpon him. All things are naked &amp; open to his eyes,<note place="margin">Gene. 17.</note> and therfore reuerently walk before him, &amp; be thou vpright.<note place="margin">Iona. 1.17.</note> He fetched Ionas from his fleeing ſhip, &amp; caſt him into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whales bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.<note place="margin">Act. 12.8.9</note> He brought his preaching Peter forth of the priſon faſt locked in with yron ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. He is preſent euer to helpe innocent Suſanna out of diſtreſſe, &amp; ready to caſt the corrupted Iudges vnto their deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued death. This was Dauids comforte, <hi>Thou Lorde art vvith me, therefore will I not feare.</hi> Let the ſame teache vs nowe to ſay, our God and Chriſt is preſent by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ayde and comforts in all troubles to aſſiſt vs: of whom then ſhall we be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayd, for thogh faſt cloſed in yron gates, through the ſtrength of our god we ſhall leape ouer the wall. And though perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for his cauſe, yet is he redy to comfort vs in all tribulation.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.3.</note> So that we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to comfort others which be in afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortes which we haue receyued our ſelues of God. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, thy carefull gouernment ſayth Dauid dothe adminiſter no ſmall ſolace vnto me, <hi>for
<pb facs="tcp:8947:19"/> thy rodde and thy ſtaffe they comfort me.</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid elegantly, dwelling in the receyued Metaphor, ſetteth foorth Gods good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment by the Shepheards rodde and ſtaffe, which rodd or Shepheards crooke is vſed of a cunning heard, to conſtrayne the declining ſheepe, to his former foldy-mates, to vrge the wanderer to his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted felowes, and to force the ſlouthfull Plodders better to paſe it: Euen ſo the Lord by his holy rod and ſtaffe of health, doth ſcourge our wandring ſteppes, and with his correcting hande, in loue, dothe ioyne vs to his Church, and if ſlouthfully we lye aloofe, he vſeth ſharper blowes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell our ſpeede to ioyne with others in the ſeruice of our god: all which is to the beſt comfort of his choſen childe. But here is named a Rod, and a Staffe, the one to correct vs, thother to defende vs. And both of theſe are doubled in the holy ſcriptures. God is ſayde to haue a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde Rod, the Rod of his loue, and the Rod of his anger.<note place="margin">Zach. 11.</note> Alſo a twofold ſtaffe: as in Zacharie the ſtaffe of beautie, and the ſtaffe of Bands. Of theſe two rods, and theſe two ſtaues, the ſcripture ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thus, Firſt Thapoſtle ſayth, that in
<pb facs="tcp:8947:19"/> loue he ſcourgeth his people, &amp; correcteth their ſinnes, leaſt they ſhould be damned with the wicked world.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.32</note> 
               <hi>When we are thus iudged</hi> (ſayth Paul, ſpeaking of gods cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for thabuſe of the Euchariſt) <hi>wee are chastened of the Lord, that we ſhould not be condemned vvith the vvorld.</hi> Behold his louing Rod. Our dayly tranſgreſſions demerite death, but his dayly mercy who willeth not the death of a ſinner,<note place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note> cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth his ſharpned ſworde into a ſmarting rod,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.8</note> thereby to worke in vs true repentance,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.10. and 2.17</note> and humble pacience. For as his hand is ſtriking,<note place="margin">Eſa. 5 4.7</note> his bowels are boyling in pitie towards vs, and with his ſpirite dothe chaunge our hartes, and ſupporteth our falling ſtate, by hys defending ſtaffe. <hi>Wherefore despiſe not</hi> (ſayth Paule) <hi>the chastening of the Lorde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 12.5.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>neyther faynt when thou arte rebuked of him. For vvhome the Lorde loueth, he chasteneth, and he ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth euery ſonne that he receyueth. Yf yee endure chastning God offereth him ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you as vnto ſonnes, for vvhat ſonne is he vvhome the father chastneth not? Yf ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yee be vvithout correction, vvhereof all be partakers, then are yee Bastardes and not Sonnes.</hi> See dearely beloued, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:8947:20"/> of our louing Father in this his rod of loue. And now it ſhould ſeme this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine to be moſte liuely, when as we ſee his heauy hande whipping our brethren with the ſmarting ſcourge of peſtilence, Irelande is therewith euery where infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Englande is infected, and this our Countrey, and Townes very neare vs. Stamford and Vppingham, greeuouſly viſited. Hereby we ought to be moued to repentaunce, knowing that for ſinne our God our ſhephearde chaſteneth vs with rebukes (that I may vſe our Prophetes words in the Pſalmes) and with his rod maketh our gallant beautie to fade away,<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.11</note> as it were a mothe fretting a garment. Euery man therefore is but vanitie: But there be ſome of you (me thinketh) that whiſpereth in my eares, thus: Syr you knowe that many of vs together with your ſelfe, God hath moſt louingly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from this peſtilent rod, in Ireland, yea and ſo, that wonderful was our ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The whole land is viſited, no towne knowne free, in the houſe where we lay ſome dead, in the ſhippe wherein we paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſeas, one or moe gone to God: and ſith our departure, the Knight, with
<pb facs="tcp:8947:20"/> whom we were twentie dayes (wayting Gods bleſſing for weſterly winds) hath in his owne perſon therwith bene ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. The which deliueraunce ſeemeth to cleare vs, in deſeruing ſo heuie a ſcourge, though called a louing rodde. So of the reſt (I deeme) ſome ſay, and wee alſo are not touched with the plague, but they whiche haue deſerued it, haue it: this doctrine therefore might beſt ſerue thoſe whiche are nowe exerciſed with his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Rodde. But to one and other of you I ſay (deare brethren) as Chriſt our louing Shephearde ſayde to the repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Pylates cruell facte, who min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled the blood of the Galileans with the ſacrifice of the Iewes, thus:<note place="margin">Luke. 13.2</note> 
               <hi>Suppoſe yee</hi> (ſaythe Chriſte) <hi>that theſe Galileans were greater ſinners then all the other Galileans, becauſe they haue ſuffered ſuche thinges? I tell you nay. But except yee amende your lyues, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſhe. Or thinke you that thoſe eyghtien vpon whom the Towre in Syloam fell and ſlewe them, that they were ſinners aboue all men that dwelt in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem? I tell you nay. But excepte ye amende your lyues, yee ſhall all likewiſe periſhe.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8947:21"/> So let Chriſt ſay to you heere preſent: That you are by my ſparing hande brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght from the plague in Irelande, that you are yet ſeuered from the ſicke here in Rutlande: it is not for that any of you, (from the Preacher to the baſeſt Hearer) haue leſſe offended, but that I woulde vſe them for your Preachers to amendement, and them ſelues to a bettered lyfe, as hereafter (yf by their example ye amende not) I will make you the lyke example to others, when they ſhall ſee my hande ſhaking ouer you. Praye for our brethren therefore, helpe too ſuccour theyr preſent neede, and repent in time, leaſt that his ſcourge of loue beeing remoued, we feele the heauy fall of his angry Rodde. Wherof our Prophete ſpeaketh in the ſeconde Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.9.</note> prophecying the vtter ruine of all thoſe that inſult agaynſt Chriſt and his choſen children. For as he is moſte louely vnto his louely ſheepe, So to the ſtubborne harted he is the God of ſtrength, who can and will correcte, or compell them to ſtoupe to his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And he is ſayde to haue an yron Rodde in reſpect of his diuine power,
<pb facs="tcp:8947:21"/> and princely dominion ouer the mightie Kinges of the earth, who with his worde doth arme the weake things of the world, agaynſt the moſte gigaunt vnder heauen. Liſe and Frogges ſhall bee to ſtrong for ſtout Pharao the mightie gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gante king of Egypt,<note place="margin">Pſ. 78.45.</note> and weake Dauid ſhall ouerthrowe the huge armies of the Philiſteans, the Syrians, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ammonites,<note place="margin">2. Sa. 10.12</note> &amp; the Moabites. The Idumeans,<note place="margin">1. Para. 18.19.</note> and the Syria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhal ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by weaknes be brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their great ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth.<note place="margin">Eſa. 37.36.38</note> Sennacherib with his Rabſekah ſhal leaue his ſiege agaynſt Ieruſalem, &amp; ſhal be broken into peeces: his owne ſonnes ſhall ſtrike him to the hart with their ſwords (the Lordes yron rod) to his vtter confuſion. And to this their vtter ſhame, the Lorde from heauen ſhal vſe but his only word, and with the breath of his mouth ſhall he make al crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures redy to be his rod, to the confuſion of the wicked. His owne prophet Eliſah ſhal cauſe blindnes to come into the eyes of the mightie hoſt, which fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the king of Syria are ſent to take him, and ſhal bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into Samaria y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie of their enemies. Bennadad the king of Aram ſhal be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled<note place="margin">2. King. 6.14.18</note> to remoue his ſiege from Samaria
<pb facs="tcp:8947:22"/> in one night,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 7.6.</note> becauſe the Lord hath made the concept of hearing of charrets &amp; horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to be his yron rod to driue them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their enemies, which by them before were brought to moſt extreme pennurie, ſo that an aſſes heade, was ſolde for foure ſchore ſiluerlinges, and a load of doues doung (to roſt the ſame) for fyue ſyluer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges. The former churches of the caſte which did degenerate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their firſt faith,<note place="margin">2. Ki. 6.25.</note> hath he with this his angry rod, caſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of the Turke, that they may beleeue lies to their deſtruction, which would not receiue the truth, when it was offered them. Chriſte in his owne perſon is this rodde of anger, to all that ſtubbornly reſiſt him.<note place="margin">2. Teſ. 2.</note> He that ſtumbleth at this Chriſte ſhall be bruſed, but vppon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer this ſtone Chriſt ſhall fall he ſhall grind the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all to poudre,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.44.</note> take hede of this angry (ſo dayly prouoked) yron rod. For as to the faithfull he is lyfe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnbeleuing &amp; obſtinate, he is the yron rod here ſpoken of. His ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, Apoſtles, preachers &amp; miniſters, hath he made to be the ſame, according to the nature of their auditory, as The Apoſtle Paule witneſſeth, ſaying: <hi>The weapons of
<pb facs="tcp:8947:22"/> our warefare are not carnall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.4.</note> 
               <hi>but mighty through God, to caſte downe holdes, caſting downe the imaginations and euery high thing that is exalted againſte the knowledge of God, &amp; bringing into captiuitie euery thought to the obedience of Chriſt. And hauing ready the vengeaunce againſt all diſobedience, when your obedience is fulfilled.</hi> O my brethren conſider your calling: ye are the ſheepe of Chriſte, what belongeth your calling: Truely to heare with reuerent obedience his voyce. What is his workmanſhippe then of you regenerate? To purge you with his rodde of loue that ye ſhould be more fruitefull, and to the greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of you his choſen: he plaigeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction with his angrye yron rodde, the wicked whiche can not but muche moleſte you, were they vnbrydled. Take heede in tyme, repent and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue his ghoſpell,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.1.</note> leaſte the former being ended, his ſecond rodde beginne to ſkoure you oute of place, for a better people.<note place="margin">Mat. 21.43</note> Thus muche for the Lordes roddes, and nowe to the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes crooke, that doubled ſtaffe, of whiche Dauid thus ſayth: <hi>Thy rodde and thy ſtaffe they comfort me.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:23"/>
            <p>As it is farre more ſafety for vs, to be vnder our ſhepheards rod, then commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or left to the woluiſhe iawes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanicall broade: So is it our beſt comfort and aſſured proſperitie to dwell vnder the reach of his moſt louing gouerment, which here is ſet forth vnto vs by the ſhepheard ſtaffe. Very ſignifica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet Zachary ſet downe the loue and anger of God, by the two ſtanes which Chriſte our ſhepheard firſt toke into his hand, and after bruſt in ſundre. And theſe be his words: <hi>I toke vnto me two ſtaues</hi> (the prophet ſpeaketh in the perſon of Chriſt) <hi>the one J called beautie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 11.7.</note> 
               <hi>and the other I called ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, &amp; J fed the ſhepe.</hi> And a little after he ſayth: <hi>Their ſoule abhorred me, and J ſayde, J vvill not feede you, that vvhich dyeth let it dye, and that vvhich periſheth let it periſhe: and let the remnant eate one another: euery one the fleſhe of his neighbour. And J toke my ſtaffe beauty and brake it, that J might diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null my couenaunt vvhich J had made vvith all people:</hi> And ſomewhat after, thus, <hi>Then brake J myne other ſtaffe, euen bandes, that J might diſſolue the brotherhoode betvvene Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah and Jſraell.</hi> By the firſte ſtaffe beauty, the Prophet vnderſtandeth that moſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant
<pb facs="tcp:8947:23"/> frame of the Iewiſhe common welth &amp; gouernment, which for the great excellencie thereof, is here called beautie. Of this ſtaffe Moſes triumphing ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thus: <hi>Keepe theſe lavves and do them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deu. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>for that is your vviſedome, and your vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the ſight of the people, vvhich ſhall heare all theſe ordinaunces, and ſhall ſay, only this people is vviſe and of vnderſtanding, and a great nation. For what nation is ſo greate vnto whom the Gods come ſo neere vnto them, as the Lord our God is neere vnto vs, in all that we call vnto him for. And what nation is ſo greate, that hath ordinaunces and lawes ſo righteous, as all this law which I ſet before you this day:</hi> But if from the conſtituted lawe moſt holy, righteous, briefe and comodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, thou caſt thine eyes to the common welth of Iſraell, euen from the king Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon to his people, thou ſhalt ſee it moſt beautifull. The conſtitution of the church in Iury as it far paſſed all popiſhe pompe (and that was maruelous) ſo was it not without a preaching office to the poſteritie of Chriſtes glorified churche. The doctrine plainely did ſet forth the way to life in Chriſt: and becauſe all this faire forme tended to this ende to keepe
<pb facs="tcp:8947:24"/> the poople of Iſraell in the limittes of their calling,<note place="margin">Gualterus in zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</note> it is aptly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes ſtaffe, and for the excelling order is moſte worthely called beauty. By the ſecond ſtaffe he vnderſtandeth the lynked loue and fraternitie in blood, which farre excelled all other kingdomes, whiche know not their originall, or are kept im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed with forre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blood. The Iewes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede all from one father Iacob, and are as touching blood al in one brotherhood. The Lord to keepe them in them ſelues, as well in externall rites as continuall Genelogies of their Tribes, did tye them together in one, that they ſhoulde not he ignorant of their pedigrie, nor ſhoulde mixt them ſelues with forreiners. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it els then the Lordes ſingular bleſſing, that notwithſtanding ſo many battailes and often troubles, ſuch diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the kingdome and long exile, in ſo many forepaſſed yeeres, they (till the day wherin the Lord brake theſe his ſtaues of beauty and bands) knowe one anothers race &amp; ofſpring for the which things ſake you may ſee howe elegantly this ſtaffe is called bands, as by the which the Iewiſh amitie was preſerued. But both theſe
<pb facs="tcp:8947:24"/> ſtaues Chriſt brake when Symony firſte purchaſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſthood in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes were oppreſſed of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; made the out caſtes of the world, which ſometime were Lordes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earthe aboue the reſt. And this couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t did God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold when after Chriſts aſſention, he ſent the Romaines to pollute: and finally to ſubuert both their eccleſiaſticall and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique gouernment. Yet ſome comforte was left them tyll the reigne of <hi>Aelius A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drianus,</hi> by whom their rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Chriſt and his word, was vtterly reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged. For he ſlewe many of them, he put the reſt to exile, and forbdd them the entraunce into their former Cyties &amp; townes, he did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them to caſt their lokes from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land of promiſe. He rammed vp the gates in Ieruſalem with ſwynes doung to the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomious reproch of the obſtinate Iewes with whome God in iuſtice had cauſed his Chriſte to breake the ſtaues of their former defence beautie &amp; bandes. And fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this tyme is it that the temple and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth in Iury is ſo ouerthrowne, that none of them can now truely tell of what linnaige or kindred he is of.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:25"/>
            <p>O Lord who can loke into this people and not quake in feare, ſo greatly bleſſed, ſo dearely loued, as to them and for them God ſpared not to gyue his ſonne in firſt and chiefe. Beſides for this he kept the whole earth to ſtand in awe of them. But now no people ſo odious eyther to God or man, as they, quite geuen ouer of god, and perſecuted of all good men. By this we are taught (that ſith all our chriſtian fraternitie dependeth vpon Chriſt whom this people diſpiſed, of whom we are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and by whom alſo we haue God to our father) ſpedely to kiſſe the ſonne leaſt he be angry,<note place="margin">Pſa. 2.12.</note> and ſo we periſhe from the right way, for vnleſſe we be at one with him, there is no accompt of vs, but as to the wicked Iewes, to whom there is no peace. The beautiful gouernment of this our lande ſo long continued vnder one monarchy, may aſſure vs of Chriſte our ſhephearde to holde our ſtay, his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſtaffe, in hande. But I feare me our demerites be ſuche, as were it not for his owne names ſake, this ſtaffe by him yet holden, would ſpedely be ſore ſhiuered. God preſerue our noble Queene, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone by his great mercy, the ſtay of our
<pb facs="tcp:8947:25"/> happy gouernment is continued, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde her we can ſee nothing but confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Our beauty is then lyke to be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into more than beggery. Farre be it from men in earth, to take this Gods of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice from heauen in hand. If any gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he not perfect, it is the Lords to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende it, yf any to be reformed, the ſame is with ſuch foreſight to be regarded, that in ſeeking to remoue the forreing matter, from the ſhepheards ſtaffe (which by lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger tyme (as a ſnayle) ſlowly hathe crept vppon it: and by latter dayes is conglu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate ſo thereto, that hardly may it be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered withoute ſome detriment) that the ſtaffe may ſtill be preſerued, without which we periſhe. To the ſhepheardes which haue this ſtaffe in hold, belongeth the polliſhing of the ſame,<note place="margin">Prou. 20.</note> and not to priuate perſons which are rather to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected therby. Our partes is to pray the head ſhepheard Chriſt, by whom kinges do reigne, ſo to frame the hartes of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian kings which are al in his hand, that they may feede the flocke committed to their charge, faithfully and in the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of their ſoule,<note place="margin">Pſ. 78.70.71.72.</note> with the ſtaffe of Chriſtes gouernment: Namely by the
<pb facs="tcp:8947:26"/> Cannon of his worde, which by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prouidence is appointed the ſtaffe of our aſſured defence. The preachers of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is into the hartes of Kinges to beat the knowledge of this truth, that they by doctrine, may know, the ſubſtanciall due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of beſt gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. The higher called to the firſt, muſt hoalpe thereto, that God our highe ſhephearde by him ſelfe, in the perſon of his princes in earth, may dayly rule ouer vs his children. So farre I lyke of the learned at this day ſeeking for redreſſe: but in no wiſe dare I alowe, that others ſhoulde be ſhut vp in hate, which cannot ioyne in all reſpects to that them ſelues do not perceiue. And I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that petition, patience, and parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is the aſcending ſtaire, to this high bleſſing. Beyonde this there ſeemeth not els to be but a chruſſhing of the ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes croke, which is the worke of god alone:<note place="margin">Zac. 11.16.</note> and to vs then no other, but the dore of deſolation, and confuſion, to our former chriſtian vnitie, which God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue for his names ſake, and purge his church, of ſnayly knurres glewed to this ſtaffe, and keepe the ſame whole &amp; ſound ouer vs to our fartheſt poſteritie, yf it
<pb facs="tcp:8947:26"/> ſtande with his good will and pleaſure. So ſhal our kingdome be beautifull, and our chriſtian brotherhoode garded with the band of Gods ſpirite, to our eternall peace in him. For the which peace onely we ought to ſtryue, for all other peace is meare warres with God. Thus much of the ſhepheardes roddes and ſtaues, and nowe we proceede to the <hi>.5.</hi> verſe, which ſayth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Thou doeſt prepare a table before me in the ſight of myne aduerſaries. Thou doſt anoynt my heade with oyle and my cup runneth ouer.</p>
               <p>Doubtles kindnes and mercy ſhall follovv me, all the dayes of my lyfe, and J ſhall remaine a long ſeaſon in the houſe of the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Though mine enemyes (ſayth Dauid) ſeeke to deſtroy me, yet thou Lorde doeſt not onely deliuer me, but alſo in deſpite of their fury dealeſt moſt liberally with me, as menne doo with their chiefeſt friendes in this our lande of Iury. Bydden to their ſumptuous feaſtes, they anoynt their heades with pleaſant Oyle, and gyue them Cuppes of large importe, and them moſte amplie fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. So haſte thou, and muche
<pb facs="tcp:8947:27"/> more aboundantly delt with me, and wilt after, for thy mercy is ſuche, as kindnes ſhall follow me during lyfe. And for this thy mercy in my prolonged dayes, I ſhall alway in them ſeeke to ſerue thee: in thy holy houſe. Becauſe I haue long trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled you, I wil omit to ſpeake here of the prouidence of God in them which be his, and perſecuted of the multitude,<note place="margin">Pſ. 61.2.5.</note> but ſuch it is, that their deuiſes the Lorde doth laugh to ſkorne, and erecteth his beloued vp to honor, maugre their berdes. Or more to ſay of the difference betwixte the papiſt and the faithful proteſtant: the one with the Iew is euer gaping after good: but after the godly, Gods bleſſing run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, them to comfort, euen as the Ryuer from Moſes Rocke flowed after Iſraell to be their drinke &amp; ſpirituall ſacrament.<note place="margin">1. Co. 10.4.</note> Or once to touch that longing luſt which ought to be in Dauids lyue (in all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian heroicall, honorable, worſhipfull, godly, riche, and meaner perſons) that is a dayly deſire to ſerue God, yea euen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of prayer with the floke of Chriſts folde.<note place="margin">Pſa. 122.1.</note> I was glad (ſaith Dauid) of thoſe which ſayde vnto me, <hi>Come we will go into the houſe of the Lorde together.</hi> Your olde
<pb facs="tcp:8947:27"/> chaples, your priuate houſes (O ye ſtates of the earth) are for the moſt part an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of great loſſe to your ſelues. Ye ſo ſeperate your ſelues from the common exerciſe of Chriſtes ſheepe. Ye lacke the doctrine which other there receiue to their greate comfort. Ye keepe your families fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace, &amp; be euill examples to the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſorte. Ye expreſſe the ſmall loue to thoſe that be like Dauid, whiche if you mende not, can not but bring you from his god &amp; our ſheheard Chriſt, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is to haue his ſheepe come together.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Where two or three be gathered together in my name</hi> (ſaith Chriſte) <hi>there am I in the middeſt of them.</hi> Gather the people ſayth God, ſanctifie the congregation, gather the Elders, aſſemble the children &amp; thoſe that ſucke the breſt, let the bridegrome go out of his chamber, and the Bride out of her cloſet, Let the Prieſts the miniſters of the Lord, weepe betweene the porch, and the Alter, and let them ſay, <hi>Spare thy people O Lord. &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioel. 2.16 17.</note> This was the order in the Apoſtles churche, as Paule affirmeth in his firſt epiſtle to the Corrin. ſaying. <hi>I prayſe you not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.17.</note> 
               <hi>that you come together not with profite, but with hurt. For firſte of all vvhen
<pb facs="tcp:8947:28"/> you come together in the churche J heare that there is diſſention among you: Againe, if therefore vvhen the vvhole church is come together in one.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.23.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In this churche were of greate byrth, lyke welth and ſtately condition, yet they came together in one they aſſembled them ſelues in the church, they kept not, ſome their priuie chaples, other their dining chambers, but moſt of all their ſléeping heades. Looke to this (you ſtates) be not ſo ſtately that you ſet your ſelues ſtiffe necked to the Lorde, frequent his houſe, adſociate his people, conioyne with his churche, to heare the Lorde by his miniſters ſpeake vnto you, that your common cry with the reſte may ioyntly pearce the eares of Gods moſt louing maieſtie, in the throne of his mercy ſeat. In hope of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hereto, I ſay nothing hereof, but as you ſee runne from the ſame in haſte to ende. But becauſe of the holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, to the which we purpoſe in the Lorde, one worde thereof and ſo an ende.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.1 2.3.4.</note> Paule the Apoſtle taketh occaſion by the temporall bleſſing of God vpon the Iſraelites in Manna and the ſtony rocke, to deliuer to the Corrinthians
<pb facs="tcp:8947:28"/> ſound doctrine in ſacraments. And yf the ſame (with the reſt of holy ſcripture) be writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our learning,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> why ſhould I forget ſo good and apt a leſſon, as both his example, our preſent miniſtration, and this our profitable texte doth offer vnto me. &amp;c. Dauid ſpeaketh of his Crowne and Diademe, with the Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices: Neither doth he forget the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comfortes that from the Lorde he dayly receiueth by the ſeales of the lords righteouſnes his ſacred ſacraments.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> The ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Gods church are only two, <hi>The lauer of baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Table of the Lorde:</hi> In the Supper at this table prepared (without our prouiſion and deſert) of God in his Chriſt, the faithfull do receiue two things, &amp; that of two ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perſons: ſacred bread &amp; wyne,<note place="margin">In the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament two things are concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> at &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> externall preaching miniſtry (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only fyt miniſtre for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame) &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward ſecret, &amp; omnipotent inuiſible worke of the holy ghoſt, (in ſoule by fayth truely fixed in chriſt) they verely eat &amp; receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very true &amp; ſubſtantiall body of Ieſus Chriſt, ſtill ſitting at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father in maieſty on hie. By faith he is receiued, by gods ſpirit he is deliuered in ſoule he
<pb facs="tcp:8947:29"/> is eaten, for the diet is ſpirituall, and can not be preſſed with mans carnall téeth. That of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter we receiue only bread and wine, the holy Apoſtle Paule fyue times telleth vs in the deliuerie therof to the Corinthians. 1 Epiſt. chap. 11. And the auncient Fathers ſay the ſame: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom S. Ciprian doth ſtand ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, and he ſayth thus of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt:<note place="margin">Cipriani de vnct. Chriſm.</note> 
               <hi>Dedit ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dominus noſter, in menſa, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore our Lorde Chriſte in his laſte ſupper which he made with his Apoſtles, gaue to them at that table, Bread &amp; wine with his owne handes: but vppon the Croſſe by the hands of the cruell tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, he gaue his body wounded for vs. <hi>Sunt quae erant</hi> (ſayth Ambroſe,<note place="margin">Ambro. de ſacra. li. 4. cap. 4.</note> ſpeaking of the Elementall bread and wine) The ſame they were they are, and are chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into another vſe. If the ſacramental bread be the very body of Chriſt after co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, then the wicked aſwell eate Chriſtes body, as the godly. But this the auncient fathers doe denie. Origen ſaith, <hi>Est verus Cibus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen. in Matth.</note> Chriſt is the true meate, which no euill and wicked man can eate. For if the wicked man could (in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament) eate the body of the Lord, then
<pb facs="tcp:8947:29"/> ſhould it not be written, <hi>Qui edit hunc pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> He that eateth this bread ſhall lyue for euer. Auguſtine ſayth:<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Io. tra. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Qui non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net in Christo, &amp;c.</hi> He that dwelleth not in Chriſte, and in whome Chriſte dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not, vndoubtedly he eateth not ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually the fleſhe and blood of Chriſte, Albeit he carnally and viſibly teare with his teeth the Sacrament of the body and blood of Chriſte. And if any man ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, why then doth Chriſt ſay, <hi>This is my body?</hi> I anſwere, it is a figuratiue ſpeach of our Sauiour, and is of him ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to a people that well were acquayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Scriptures phraſe in Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. So is Circumciſion called the Couenaunt of the Lorde, when it is but the ſigne of the Lordes Couenaunt. The Couenaunt it ſelfe was, <hi>I will be thy God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17.10</note> 
               <hi>and thou ſhalt be my people.</hi> And therefore Circumciſion is called in the ſame chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that which in it ſelfe it remayneth to be, namely the Signe, and not the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt. <hi>And it ſhall be</hi> (ſayth God) <hi>a ſigne of the Couenaunt betwixt thee and me.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Paſcall Lambe is called <hi>Tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus domini,</hi> the paſſing by of the Lord, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the comming of Chriſte, yet the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:8947:30"/> by his angel paſſed but once in al through the land of Egipt,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.</note> and therfore verily &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dede, that ſacrament could not be the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſing of the Lord. This is the vſe of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, ſayth Augu.<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Leuit. 17. <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.26</note> that the ſignes which ſignifie, are called by the names whiche they do repreſent, as thus: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eares of corne <hi>ſeptem anni ſunt,</hi> are ſeuen yeres. The Rocke was Chriſte. &amp;c. And in another place he ſayth, <hi>The Lord doubted not to ſay, This is my body, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he gaue <hi>ſignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corporis</hi> the ſigne of his body.</hi> So good chriſtian Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, the words of Chriſt, as of him they were ſpoken, are ſacramentally to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode. So that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>This is my body,</hi> we are to take it thus: this is the repreſenting, &amp; to the faithfull the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting ſigne of my body. That theſe words of Chriſt are figuratiuely ſpoken, Augu.<note place="margin">Augu. de doct. chri. lib. 3.</note> alſo witneſſeth in his booke <hi>De do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina christiana.</hi> But that the faythful do eate by the worke of the ſpirite &amp; Chriſtes diuine power his very body and blood in the true vſe of the Lords ſupper, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes in god approueth, who euer was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to his people, that his faithful pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the Sacraments promiſed. Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion promiſed his continuall ayde, &amp; that
<pb facs="tcp:8947:30"/> he would be their god, and they ſhould be his people. Search the Scriptures, &amp; ſee,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note> if euer any people were ſo guerdoned, or had the preſence of God ſo neare them, or were any people ſo proſpered ſo long as they continued with circumciſed harts in his holy couenant? Did not the Lord by his angel performe that in dede, which he promiſed by his <hi>paeſah,</hi> his ſacramentall paſſeouer?<note place="margin">Exo. 12.12.13.28.29.</note> Did he not paſſe by the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites houſe tied to this Couenant, &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued all the firſt borne in Egypt. So no doubt he truely feedeth the faithfull with not only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precious body in himſelf, not ſtouping one inch yet fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fathers Throne, or giuing his body to be rent into peces with our mortal teeth, but in ſuch a diuine ſort as our tongs can not vtter, bicauſe our or thy capacities ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue the maner how, further the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſight of his noble creature y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhining ſun. The ſunne in his globe and perſon doth kepe &amp; continue his ſpheare &amp; circle in the Zodiake, &amp; yet doth he by the decree and prouident power of God, light vs, warm vs, comforte vs, and renewe our blood and bodies, and as we may ſaye by bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed ſpeache, geueth vs lyfe, by his
<pb facs="tcp:8947:31"/> heauenly beames, the ordinarie conducts from him felfe, with his very liuing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce. Sith thus we haue ſo elegant a ſhadow, of our Sauiour Chriſtes body verily feding vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are his in earth: let vs not diſtruſt, or further deſcant howe the Lord can (ſith we know not how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne doth his office, but feele it ſo to be) but let vs beleeue that the Lord by his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite doth feede vs, and in deede with his very body &amp; blood, from heauen, as veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as his miniſter at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table in earth doth geue vs the ſacred ſymboles of his holy body, whiche in their former nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine not other then bread &amp; wine. And with that mind that our father Abraham did receiue the ſacrament of circumciſion, let vs folow &amp; approch the Lordes table. That is, ſo taccept with faythful harte in hand,<note place="margin">Ro. 4.11.12</note> the holy Myſteries, as the ſeales of righteouſnes, that God will giue vs the ſame that he affyrmeth them to be, and in ſuch ſort as the ſame is to be diſtributed vnto vs effectually in ſpirite &amp; truth. Let vs examine &amp; trie our ſelues whether we be in the fayth,<note place="margin">2. Corinth.</note> let vs wel conſider of our ſteppes whether we be ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding or falling before our God, let vs caſt from vs our
<pb facs="tcp:8947:31"/> former ills, &amp; put vpon vs Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; his obedience. Let vs confeſſe our daily ſinnes, &amp; approch with louing feare &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence vnto this table of attonement. Finally repent &amp; beleeue the Goſpel. Let the Papiſt depart from all his ignoraunt ſuperſtition, &amp; receyue the doctrine of the holy written ſcriptures vnfaignedly. Let the carnal goſpeller, the Atheiſt, be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at his filthy life &amp; ſkoffing girds, caſt at the truth. Let the Auncient harlot hate his whordome, and bath his beaſtly body in the blood of Chriſt by repentant fayth. Let the couetous ſtretche out his hande vnto the poore, &amp; ſhut vp his eyes from worldly thirſt. Let the courtly Dames (&amp; you here preſent) cut ſhort the phantaſies of vaine deſires, and rather couet to come behind the laſhing pride of theſe ill days,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> then ſeeke to folow the vntamed faſhion of this wicked world.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.32.</note> And pray with Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid, that your eyes may be faſt ſhut from beholding our to to much, &amp; abhominable vanities. Let the contentious ceaſſe their brawling ſtriffe, and with vs in one by the Lordes ſpirite of truth, aſcende to the Lordes ſacrament of vnitie &amp; loue. That this grace may come to euery of vs, and
<pb facs="tcp:8947:32"/> to the whole Church of god this Church of England &amp; Ireland, and therein to the Quenes maieſtie Elizabeth, her honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Councelours and Potentates, Gods ſpiritual Preachers and Miniſters, to all Magiſtrates &amp; gouernours, as well here preſent as abſent, and to this congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a member of the ſayd Church, let vs the louing ſheepe of our cheefe Shepherd Chriſte, by the comfort &amp; direction of his holy ſpirite, humbly at the hands of our moſt merciful Father, for the loue he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to Chriſte his only begotten ſonne, and in his name craue it, ſaying, <hi>O our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whiche arte in heauen, &amp;c. Graunt, O Lorde, that into the vvords vvhich this day, and at other times, through thy great mercy vve haue graciouſly heard, vve may be effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually transformed, through Christe our head Shepheard and Lorde.</hi> To whom together with thee, O Father, and the holy Ghoſt, three diſtinct perſons, and one eternall God, be all honour and glory, power and dominion, now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Laus Deo per Christum.</hi>
               <date>
                  <hi>1. Ian. 1575</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:32"/>
            <head>To the right vvorshipfull Syr William Fitzwilliam Knight, late Lorde deputie of Irelande: <hi>A. Anderſon the minister of Christes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Goſpell, vvisheth Chriſt our Lorde, vvith his vvhole merites.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>All vppon me (ſayth God) in the day of thy trouble, and I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer thee. Greater troubles with leſſe comfortes than in the raging Seas, can not be founde, as thoſe with Dauid muſt confeſſe which occupie their buſines in greate waters. This daungerous Iourney, as among many others ye are in the Lordes name to aduenture, ſo vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe this preparatiue to your godly hart, and by and with the ſame in aſſured hope of Gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce for his Chriſt, approche his mercy ſeate. The haſt we haue, and gaping hope for Weſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly winds, will not permit long leyſure, to proyue this ſodayne frame. Take it (Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) as it is, and accept the good will of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, vſe it at your neede to the Lordes prayſe, and your preſent comfort, which is my harty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. And I ſhall dayly pray the Lorde for you, and vs, that we may ſpeedely imbarke, and ſafely arriue in Englande through Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ayde, the maſter of our ſhip. </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At <hi>Holme Patricke</hi> in Irelande. <date>
                     <hi>17.</hi> October. <hi>1575.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in <hi>Dom. A. Anderſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:33"/>
            <head>A forme of prayer for ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men and paſſengers to vſe in the ſayling Shippe.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A confeſſion of our ſinnes to God.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Almighty God and moſt righteous, we thy deare children, here encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with theſe thy mighty creatures, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> windes, the huge ſeas and ſayling ſhip, do acknowledge and confeſſe our ſelues, and euery of vs, to be miſerable ſinners, and from our firſt cradles depely to haue offended thy diuine maieſtie. Our ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall thoughtes be corrupted, our ſundry hartes and acts are polluted, our ſynnes cannot be hid from thee. We hartely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them O Lord, els ſhould our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences condemne vs, becauſe our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions beare witnes againſt vs. But thou art the God of our ſaluation and to vs thy children the beſte father, full of mercyes, riche in compaſſion, ſlowe to wrath, and moſt ready to forgiue the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinner calling vpon thee. And ſithe it is the worke of thy moſt holy ſpirite to mollifie the ſtony harted, and to chaunge the fleſhly hart into a ſpirituall ſoule:<note place="margin">Eze. 36.</note> We moſt humbly beſech thee for thy Chriſtes
<pb facs="tcp:8947:33"/> ſake, to graunt vs thy holy ſpirite, take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from vs our ſtony and gyue vs hartes of fleſhe, and into them power thy graces, &amp; turne vs vnto thee. Thy holy law im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print in our ſoules, and giue vs to walke in thy ſtatutes, during theſe our naturall lyues. Bow downe thine eare and heare vs, and with thy fauourable countenance loke vpon vs, behold our place, and cauſe of cry. Our ſhip is ſubiect to ſubuerſion, if thy holy hande direct vs not in merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prouidence. Gyue, O lord the ſweete and pleſant gale, in thy name of vs to be deſired in vehement ſtormes (by thee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to puniſh and proue vs) aſſiſt vs with thy ſtrength and ſpirite of comfort. Loke vpon our mediatour Chriſt, and through him pitie vs, and in the bowels of thy mercy, conduct vs to the hauen of vs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired if it be thy will. Then ſhall we ſing and prayſe thy name, and ſhew thy won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the deepe, and our ſoules ſhall confeſſe that though the ſeas be mightie,<note place="margin">Pſa. 93.5.</note> yet thou, O God, art of moſt might ouer them. Let vs not be tempted further gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God, then that our ſtrength in thee ſhall counteruaile, and graunt the euent proſperous, Glad our hartes with ſafety
<pb facs="tcp:8947:34"/> on ſhore, and make vs mindfull of thy mercies. Gyue vs we beſeche thee, true fayth, firme hope, and ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t loue in thee, keepe vs alwayes thine, and graunt thy Chriſt for euer ours, in whoſe name for our ſelues and all other in our condition, with the reſt of thy churche we call vnto thee, thus: O our father which arte in heauen, halowed be thy name, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>A pſalme.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 93.5.</note>The waues of the ſea are mighy and rage horribly, but yet the Lord that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth on high is mightier.<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">23.</note>They that go down to the ſea in ſhips, &amp; occupie their buſines in great waters.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">24.</note>Theſe men ſee the workes of the Lord, and his wonders in the deepe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">25.</note>For at his worde the ſtormy wind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth which lifteth vp the waues therof.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">26.</note>They are caried vp to heauen &amp; downe againe to the deepe, their ſoule melteth in them becauſe of their trouble.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">27.</note>They reele to &amp; fro, and ſtagger like a dronken man, &amp; are at their wittes ende.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">28.</note>So when they cry vnto the Lorde in their trouble, hee deliuereth them out of their diſtreſſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8947:34"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">29.</note>For he maketh the ſtormy windes to ceaſſe, ſo that the waues therof are ſtill.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">30.</note>Then are they glad becauſe they are at reſt, and ſo he bringeth them to the hauen where they would be.</p>
               <p>O that men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his goodnes, &amp; declare the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which he doth for the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men.</p>
               <q>Glory be to the Father. &amp;c.</q>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">The leſſon <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.13.</note>ANd when Ieſus was entred with his diſciples into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhip, there aroſe a gret tempeſt in the ſea, ſo that the ſhip was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with waues, but he was a ſleepe. Then his Diſciples awoke him, ſaying, Maſter ſaue vs, we periſhe. And he ſayde vnto them, why are ye fearefull O ye of little faith? Then he aroſe and rebuked the windes and the ſea, and ſo there was a greate calme. And the men marueled, ſaying, what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is this that both winds and ſea obey him.</q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">If the Sea be rough. </note>Out of the deepe O Lord we call vpon thee, heare vs, O God, and haue mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.</note>We haue ſore prouoked thine anger (O Lord) thy wrath is waxed hot, &amp; thy heuy diſpleaſure is ſore kindled againſt vs.</p>
               <p>But rebuke vs not in thine indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither chaſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in thy diſpleaſure.<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8947:35"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iudit 8.</note>In deede we acknowledge that all our puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our deſeruings.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 11.</note>But yet of thy mercy (O Lord) correct vs to amendement, and plague vs not to our deſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sap. 11. Pſa. 25.</note>Turne thee vnto vs and haue mercy, for we are deſolate and in great miſery.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 79.</note>So we that be thy people and the ſhepe of thy paſture, ſhall giue thee thankes for euer, and will be alwaies ſhewing forth thy prayſe, to all generations. Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lorde God the Father of comforts and God of all ſolace, which art euer myndfull of thy mercy, and carefull to keepe promiſe, who alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeſt vs to call vpon thee in our troubles, with hope of full releaſe at the brinke of our deepe daungers, we thy poore children craue thy hande now to helpe vs, which are deſtitute of further ayde in earth, then this our litle ſhip. We are inuironed with theſe huge roring ſeas, horribly raging, and breaking in vpon vs. The winds are vehement, &amp; grow to increaſe in ſtormes, our ſinnes be heuy, and Satan ſeeketh to ſinke vs. In our ſelues we diſtruſt, but
<pb facs="tcp:8947:35"/> in thy mercy we repoſe our earneſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and in the humbled ſtate of theſe our ſoules, we beſeeche thee to heare vs. Graunt vs thy Chriſt his preſence in our ſhip. Awake, O bleſſed ſauiour, &amp; help vs leſt we periſh. Thou ſeeſt our caſe &amp; cauſe of crye, thou knoweſt our weaknes, O Lord encreaſe our fayth. Commaund the winds to ceaſe their violence, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptroll the ſeas, and ſet them quite vnder vs. Keepe whole our maſtes, prouide ſafety to our ſayle, holde ſteddy our helme, and be thy ſelf the maſter of our ſhip. Giue vs grace to haue like care to ſerue thee in ſeming &amp; ſuppoſed ſecuritie, as we haue deſire to receiue thy helpe in this our preſent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie. Keepe vs euer to be thine, and vouchſafe to ſtand for vs to thy Fathers iuſtice. Conduct vs to land, and ſafely ſet vs to our ſeuerall dwellinges for thy names ſake. Bleſſe our ſoules with thy ſpirite, &amp; be mercifull to our Church and Queene, her honorable Deputies, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, Preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; Magiſtrates. Geue them and vs faythful harts to heare thy worde, &amp; encreaſe thy good giftes in the teachers of the ſame. Finally, our ſelues, our ſoules &amp; bodies, we commit into thy
<pb facs="tcp:8947:36"/> mercifull handes, deliuer vs at thy good pleaſure for thy holy names ſake, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, to whom with the Father and the holy ghoſt, be all honour and glory now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>But if the Seas be quiet, and paſſage pleaſaunt, then ſay thus, and pray.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lorde our good God, howe excellent is thy name, wonderfull are thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, but thy mercy farre aboue meaſure. If we deſcende into our conſciences to ponder the poyſe of our ſinne, what may we looke for but vengeaunce, beholding thee for iuſt? Theſe ſenſles Creatures, the winde and ſeas, doo dayly ſerue thee in ſilent obedience: and all other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior created things doo euer yeelde thee obſequie. But we for whom all theſe are made, and dayly are benefited by them, do neuer ſtande vpright before thee. And at this preſent Lord we fele the truth of thy louing promiſe giue to all them that truſt in thee. For thou haſt called away the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſtormes (the correction of ſinne and triall of fayth) and ſente vnto vs this pleaſant gale, hauing the winde ſeruiſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:8947:36"/> to our humble deſires, &amp; theſe migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie waters to worke our willing effects. Vouchſafe vs pardon by Chriſte, for our iniquities, and the continuaunce of this pleaſaunt paſſing, vntill we be ariued the port (in thee) of vs deſired. Keepe vs we pray thee O heauenly father, from all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils in the ſea, and ſaue vs by thy mighty hande in earth. Guyde vs with thy ſpirit in the ſhip of thy holy church, through the raging ſeas of this wicked world, &amp; bring vs through true fayth ſafely to the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall hauen of our inheritaunce, that there with the companie of al heauenly paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, we may prayſe thee euerlaſtingly. Graunt vs, and thy whole churche, theſe our requeſtes, for Chriſte our Lorde thy ſonnes ſake. In whoſe name we make to thy mercy our petition thus: <hi>O our father which art in heauen. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Hauing ſafely arriued let the godly company together ſay or ſing the 103 Pſalme, and then this thankſgeuing, thus.</head>
               <p>AL honor &amp; prayſe we yeelde to thee O God our louing father, who in thy great mercy, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding our former
<pb facs="tcp:8947:37"/> liues, &amp; preſent ſins, ſome diſtruſting thy louing helpe, ſome not caring to cal vpon thee (and ſome moſt deſperately blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thy holy name) haſt thus moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully deliuered vs, and to this ſafety on land in thy gret mercy brought vs. Now Lord again we beſeech thee to defend vs, that hauing ſafely paſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſurging ſeas, we be not, through our weaknes, &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temtation, drowned in the volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Riuers of fleſhly luſtes, or choked with the foggie miſts of popiſh or carnal practiſes, but that we may attende vpon the ſonne of righteouſnes, Chriſte our Lorde, and may be conducted to the haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our celeſtiall Ieruſalem, by the moſte pleaſant purifying winde, the ſpirite of truth. Which ſpirit as he bloweth where he luſteth, ſo vouchſafe him euer to take vs with him during our naturall liues, in the faythful and true ſeruing of thee, and neuer leaue vs deſtitute of his holy aide, vntil thou haſt (for thy chriſtes ſake) crowned vs in glory. To whom with thee and the ſame holy ghoſt, three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and our one &amp; only God, be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and glory for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
               <closer>Laus Deo per Christum.</closer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:8947:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
